<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Technical Blogs on Harsh Mishra</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/</link><description>Recent content in Technical Blogs on Harsh Mishra</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>© 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 19:41:23 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>To the Layman: Observability is not APM</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/o11y-is-not-apm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/o11y-is-not-apm/</guid><description>This post is a small attempt at explaining Observability to any software developer or sysadmin, regardless of the experience level.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/o11y-is-not-apm/featured.png"/></item><item><title>Why I ditched Ubuntu ?</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/ubuntu-rant/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/ubuntu-rant/</guid><description>As a long time Ubuntu User for 13 years, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally made the decision to swap out Ubuntu on all my machines, my VMs, my personal laptops and my secondary work laptop to Debian and Bluefin. This comes after years of frustration, Canonical&amp;rsquo;s pure neglect of basic &amp;ldquo;Ubuntu Ideals&amp;rdquo;, on the desktop front</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/ubuntu-rant/featured.png"/></item><item><title>How to Write Incremental Database Migrations for PostgreSQL Clusters</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/postgres-inc-migrations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/postgres-inc-migrations/</guid><description>This article discusses best practices for versioned schema changes, safe column modifications, and managing replica lag across database clusters. Includes practical patterns for transactions, data batching, and rollback strategies to maintain high availability in production.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/postgres-inc-migrations/featured.png"/></item><item><title>How to port-forward from EC2 instances without the need for opening any SSH ports or creating Bastion hosts</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/aws-ec2-portforward/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/aws-ec2-portforward/</guid><description>Learn how to port-forward from EC2 instances in private subnets without opening SSH ports or setting up bastion hosts. This AWS SSM Session Manager guide provides a secure, cost-effective, and simple solution for EC2 access and port forwarding.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/aws-ec2-portforward/featured.png"/></item><item><title>What YouTube Tutorials Don't Tell You About DevOps &amp; SRE (A Fresher's POV).</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/yt-rant/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/yt-rant/</guid><description>This article highlights the gap between idealized YouTube tutorials and real-world DevOps/SRE work, emphasizing fundamentals, debugging, and system reliability over superficial projects.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/yt-rant/featured.png"/></item><item><title>Exploring Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG): enhancing LLMs with external knowledge</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/rag-explore/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/rag-explore/</guid><description>Explore how Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) can enhance Large Language Models (LLMs) like ChatGPT by leveraging external knowledge sources. Understand the fundamentals of LLMs, the limitations of standalone models, and the key components of a RAG-based application.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/rag-explore/featured.png"/></item><item><title>Understanding MLOps from a software engineers' perspective</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/mlops-from-se-prespective/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/mlops-from-se-prespective/</guid><description>A comprehensive overview of MLOps for software engineers, covering key concepts, challenges, and best practices. Learn about knowledge silos, the MLOps lifecycle, automation, versioning, experiment tracking, and more.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/mlops-from-se-prespective/featured.png"/></item><item><title>How to Collect Kubernetes Node Metrics with Node-Exporter Using CronJobs ?</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/node-exporter-blog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/node-exporter-blog/</guid><description>This article focuses on leveraging cron-jobs in Kubernetes to pull host metrics from all nodes in Kubernetes and save them as log files. A few days ago I was asked to solve this problem as part of an interview process for an SRE position. The problem is a very nice way to brush up your skills in monitoring. So, I decided to share it with all readers.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/node-exporter-blog/featured.png"/></item><item><title>Quick Read: How do you find Long Running and Blocking Queries in Postgres?</title><link>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/slowquery-postgres/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hmx86.cloud/articles/slowquery-postgres/</guid><description>Recently, I was working on a custom Observability suite where I needed to monitor long-running and blocking queries running on a HA Postgres Cluster running over Kubernetes using Patroni.</description><media:content xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hmx86.cloud/articles/slowquery-postgres/featured.png"/></item></channel></rss>